Hi everyone! Welcome to Dive Into Ansible. I'm James Spurin,
and I'm your instructor for this course.
I've worked in the IT industry for over 20 years for many leading companies
including Nomura, Goldman Sachs, Dell EMC, when I worked there it was just EMC,
Hitachi, Virgin Internet, and one of the first ever Internet providers in the UK
Demon Internet. While I was working, I also studied,
and I was one of the first to complete an online Masters in Software Engineering
at Liverpool University. Personally I love OpenSource and DevOps
technology, as well as Ansible, the likes of Docker,
which we'll also make you solve on this course.
In the OpenSource community itself,
I regularly give back. I'm the creator of
XMLdataset, a library for handling XML, featured on the Awesome Python list.
I maintain a popular Docker image for another OpenSource
software project called Hexo, a framework for
creating static websites. I also contribute
to a variety of OpenSource projects
including Ansible, which of course, this course is about.
Ansible, which of course, this course is about.
The course originally started back in 2018, as
Mastering Ansible, and since then it's been
refreshed and updated to what you see here, as
Dive Into Ansible. I regularly review and maintain
it, and so far, it's supported Ansible, right
through from version 2, to the current version.
With this course, I bring you a fantastic lab
experience, which directly mirrors what I'm
actually using in the lessons. Where Ansible and
all of the associated lab hosts are directly
accessible from your web browser, you can run this
locally on your own system, or via Google Cloud.
You get your Ansible control host, free Ubuntu, and
free CentOS systems. We intentionally use
different Linux systems so that we can really see
the power and versatility of Ansible when
targeting the systems simultaneously. By the way,
in this course, the container images and the
environment that I've created for the lab are
also OpenSource, so these are also available for
you to use yourself, or even just for learning
purposes. Personally, I now focus full time on
education and content, as the founder of this
company, DiveInto and especially love hearing and
connecting with people like yourselves who
clearly share the same interests in technology.
For whatever reason, you've decided to learn
Ansible today, take a moment and connect with me
on both Twitter, and LinkedIn. This course is
provided with a huge library of examples that
relate to each chapter, and has been designed so
that you can actually work through this in the
best way that suits you. Rather than me actually
dictating how you should learn, you can actually
choose your own preferred learning path. So you
can just watch through the videos if you rapidly
need to learn Ansible in a short amount of time.
Alternatively, you can follow the course and
directly run and interact with all of the examples
yourselves in exactly the same way that I'm using
throughout the course. Or again, you can use the
content as a reference and create your own content
based on what is taught. Regardless of which
approach you choose, at the end, you'll also have
a full library of resources that you can make use
of when you're using Ansible. So onto the
course content; we're currently in the first
section and after this overview, we'll start with
an introduction to Ansible. Next, we'll install
Docker, which is a requirement for our lab
environment. We'll configure the Ansible lab,
we'll set up a trusted relationship between our
hosts with SSH and we'll configure the course code
repository. In Section three, we'll look at
Ansible architecture and design. We'll start by
configuring Ansible where we'll make use of the
awesome Ansible command line tool to validate and
test our configuration. We'll also look at
inventories and modules, and how we can interact
with modules direct from the command line. In
section four, we'll get started with Playbooks.
We'll take a look at YAML, the various
sections that make up a Playbook, the use of
variables and facts, how to use templating with
Jinja2, and we'll create and execute a fully
fledged web server and website project with
Ansible. In Section five, we'll take a look at
some of the more common Playbook modules. We'll
look at Dynamic Inventories, both how to use them,
and how to create them. The use of register and
when for capturing information. The various ways
of using loops; we'll look at the performance
aspects with different means of execution such as
asynchronous, serial and parallel. Task delegation,
how to make a task run on a specific target, and
support magic variables and support blocks; and the
Ansible Vault for securing information. In Section
six, we'll see how we can structure Ansible
Playbooks through the use of includes and imports.
Tags, that will allow us to reuse specific entities
and roles where we can break our tasks into
reusable components. In Section seven, we'll make
use of popular areas with Ansible such as AWS, and
Docker. In Section eight, we'll create our own
modules and plugins. Section nine covers other
Ansible resources and areas such as
troubleshooting. Lastly, section 10 is
supplementary, and within this other areas and
resources that you may find useful. So with that
introduction and summary, let's dive into the next
video, Introduction to Ansible.
[No audio]